<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of the famous conference held about religion at Paris between M. Bossuet, Bishop of London, late tutor to the Dauphin, and Monsieur Claude, minister of the reformed church at Charenton at the Countess of Royes house in the presence of several persons of the first quality at the request of Mademoiselle de Duras, daughter to the famous Marshal de Turenne, she being then upon changing her religion  / translated from the French copy, as it was lately published by Monsieur Claude.</title>
            <title>Conference avec M. Claude minstre de charenton, sur la matier̀e de l'eǵlise. English</title>
            <author>Bossuet, Jacques Bénigne, 1627-1704.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28848</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3790</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15735</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13146899</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13146899</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98072</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28848)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98072)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 446:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of the famous conference held about religion at Paris between M. Bossuet, Bishop of London, late tutor to the Dauphin, and Monsieur Claude, minister of the reformed church at Charenton at the Countess of Royes house in the presence of several persons of the first quality at the request of Mademoiselle de Duras, daughter to the famous Marshal de Turenne, she being then upon changing her religion  / translated from the French copy, as it was lately published by Monsieur Claude.</title>
                  <title>Conference avec M. Claude minstre de charenton, sur la matier̀e de l'eǵlise. English</title>
                  <author>Bossuet, Jacques Bénigne, 1627-1704.</author>
                  <author>Claude, Jean, 1619-1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. C. for Thomas Malthus ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Religion --  17th century --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98072:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98072:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RELATION OF THE Famous Conference HELD ABOUT RELIGION AT PARIS, BETWEEN <hi>M. Boſſuet, Biſhop of Condom</hi> (late Tutor to the <hi>Dauphin</hi>) AND Monſieur Claude, Miniſter of the Reformed Church at <hi>Charenton;</hi> AT The Counteſs of <hi>Royes</hi> houſe, in the Preſence of ſeveral Perſons of the firſt Quality, at the Requeſt of <hi>Mademoiſelle de Duras,</hi> Daughter to the Famous Marſhal <hi>de Turenne,</hi> ſhe being then upon Changing her Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated from the</hi> French <hi>Copy, as it was lately Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by Monſieur</hi> Claude.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>H. C.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Malthus,</hi> at the <hi>Sun</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:98072:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98072:2"/>
            <head>A TRUE AND EXACT ACCOUNT OF THE FAMOUS CONFERENCE BETWEEN THE Biſhop of Condom, AND Monſieur CLAUDE.</head>
            <head type="sub">An Account of what paſſed in the Converſation which the Biſhop of <hi>Condom</hi> the <hi>Dauphins</hi> Tutor, had with Monſieur <hi>Claude,</hi> at the Counteſs of <hi>Royſes</hi> houſe, in the preſence of Mademoiſelle <hi>Marchalle de Lorge,</hi> the Counteſs <hi>de Roys, Mademoiſelle de Duras,</hi> the Marquiſs <hi>de Miremont, Mademoiſelle de Roucy,</hi> and <hi>Monſieur Cotton.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome dayes before this Converſation <hi>Mademoiſelle de Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi> went to ſee <hi>Monſieur Claude,</hi> whom ſhe told ſhe had ſome Scruples about Religion, and took out of her poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket a Paper, which had been given her, containing ſome paſſages of S. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> touching the <hi>Euchariſt;</hi> to which M. <hi>Claude</hi> made anſwer, and then fell to ſhowing her by other paſſages, that the Doctrine of that Father upon this Subject was the ſame with what was taught at <hi>Charenton,</hi> and herewith ſhe ſeemed ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>On the morrow Monſieur <hi>Claude</hi> chancing to ſee her at the Counteſs of <hi>Royſes</hi> houſe, after a pretty long Diſcourſe, ſhe told him, ſhe could wiſh he would have in her preſence a Conference with ſome <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Doctor or other. M. <hi>Claude</hi> made anſwer, That this was in no wiſe practiſed, that ſuch <hi>Conferences</hi> might have Dangerous conſequences, and that ſhe knew very well that the State of thoſe of the Reformed Religion in <hi>France,</hi> and in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar at <hi>Paris,</hi> obliged 'em to uſe many meaſures of Prudence and of Pre-caution: But ſaid ſhe, <hi>What courſe would you take if by Chance you met with any of thoſe Gentlemen, and that you were urged upon Points of Religion, ſure you'd not abandon your Cauſe?</hi> In ſuch
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98072:3"/> a caſe, ſaid M. <hi>Claude,</hi> I would avoid entring into Diſpute as much as poſſible I could, but being forced to it I would give a Reaſon of my Faith, and in thoſe unforeſeen Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, people are not us'd to flinch and run away. But why added he, d'ye ask me this Queſtion? That's not the matter in Diſpute.</p>
            <p>Two daies afterwards, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Counteſs of <hi>Roy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> told M. <hi>Claude,</hi> how endeavours were us'd to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave him meet as if i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by. Chance with M. <hi>de Condom,</hi> and how ſhe had thought it fitting to give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>otice of that Deſign. If I we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to meet ſaid he, with any one, I ſhould rather chooſe it ſhould be with M. <hi>de Condom</hi> than any other, Becauſe he is a Wiſe, Honourable and Underſtanding Man, and for whom I have a great Eſteem and Conſideration; but being as I am a Publique Perſon, methinks this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſineſs does deſerve to be well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght on and weighed. Sho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly after he gave an account of this buſineſs to two of his Frie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t to viſit a Perſon of Quality of an extraordinary Merit and conſummated Prudence, with whom it was concluded, that this Rencounter with M. <hi>de Condom</hi> was abſolutely to be avoided. The Reaſons were, that People already knew <hi>Mademoiſelle de Duras</hi> was wholly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to Change her Religion, that according to all appearances, ſhe only demanded a Conference, to do it with the more Sol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mnity, and to make uſe of it as a Pretext, and that what ſucceſs ſoever it might have, 'twould not hinder her from Changing, or from ſaying ſhe had not been ſatisfyed; and that the <hi>Gazette</hi> alſo would not fail to make it an Article. The Perſon of Quality, who was conſulted, took upon him to viſit the Counteſs of <hi>Roye,</hi> and make her reliſh theſe Reaſons. And ſhe reliſh'd 'em indeed and eas'ly comprehended their Strength. But notwithſtanding all ſhe could do, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lay not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n her power to diſſwade <hi>Mademoiſelle de Duras</hi> from her firſt intention. This Lady compla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned highly of being abandoned, ſaying this was e'en what ſhe had often been reproach'd with, that the <hi>Miniſters</hi> dare not appear before the <hi>Catholick</hi> Doctors. To which ſhe added Tears, to touch the Counteſs her Siſter, by all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of means, proceeding even to proteſt, that if People did but know what Good this would do her, they would certainly have this Charity for her.</p>
            <p>This obliged the Counteſs of <hi>Roye</hi> to endeavour the bringing about the Interview of M. <hi>de Condom,</hi> with M. <hi>Claude,</hi> and ſhe did it to that purpoſe that M <hi>Claude</hi> found himſelf as it were forced to grant it her, that ſo he might not be expoſed to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of thoſe of the contrary Religion. She aſſured how M. <hi>de Condom</hi> had told her, that he wiſhed this Interview might be by form of Rencounter, that it might not be publiſhed in the world, and that there might be no affecting to ſpeak of it on either ſide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tueſday</hi> the firſt of <hi>March,</hi> about two a Clock in the afternoon, M. <hi>Claude</hi> went alone to the Counteſs of <hi>Royes</hi> houſes, whither came preſently after <hi>Madame la Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchalle de Lorge, Mademoiſelle de Duras, M. le Marquis de Miremont,</hi> and M. <hi>Cotton.</hi> About a quarter of an hour after M. <hi>de Condom</hi> came alone.</p>
            <p>The firſt Civilities being over, and all the Company ſeated, M. <hi>de Condom</hi> adreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his ſpeech to M. <hi>Claude,</hi> told him, That he had been deſirous of ſeeing him, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to him ſome things of the practice of thoſe of his Religion, which he thought entirely contrary to their Principles. That thoſe things conſiſted firſt of all, in an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of their Diſcipline, which orders, That in caſe, there ariſes any Contention touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Doctrine, the Queſtion ſhall be decided in the Conſiſtory, by the Word of God, and that in caſe, they do not acquieſce, it ſhall be removed to the Provincial Synod, and from thence to the National Synod, <hi>where the entire and final Reſolution ſhall be made by the Word of God, and to which thoſe who ſhall refuſe to acquieſce ſhall be Excommunicated.</hi> That in the ſecond place, he produces a Formulary of Letter-Miſſive to the National Synods, drawn up in the Synod of <hi>Vitre,</hi> for to be thence forward followed in the Provinces, by which People promiſe to <hi>Submit themſelves to all that ſhall be reſolved on in that Holy Aſſembly, to be obedient thereunto, and to execute it from point to point, being perſuaded,</hi> ſays the <hi>Formulary, That God will provide therein, and conduct you by his Holy Spirit, in all Truth and Equity, by the Rule of his Word.</hi> That beſides this he produced an Act of the National Synod of <hi>Charen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98072:3"/> held in 1644. wherein is condemned the Opinion of the <hi>Independants,</hi> who will not allow that particular Churches depend on Colloquies and Synods; but that every one may govern it ſelf, by its own laws. Now that <hi>Act</hi> does expreſly mention, that this Sect <hi>opens a door to all manner of Irregularities and Extravagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, that it takes away all manner of applying a Remedy, and that if it were ſuffered, there might ariſe as many Religions as Pariſhes.</hi> In ſhort, he produced an <hi>Act</hi> of the National Synod of <hi>Sainte Foy,</hi> by which upon ſome overtures of Re-union with thoſe of the Confeſſion of <hi>Augſbourg,</hi> the Synod names Deputies to go and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with them; to whom was given full power of granting and concluding all the points that ſhould be brought into deliberation, whether concerning Doctrine, or any other thing, concerning the good and repoſe of all the Churches, proceeding ſo far as to inſert their reſults in the Confeſſion of the Faith: The Concluſion he drew from all this was, That thoſe of the Religion of M. <hi>Claude,</hi> did themſelves acknowledge that to preſerve the Unity of the Church, it was Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſubmit ones Judgment, and to render an Entire and abſolute Obedience to Eccleſiaſtical Aſſemblies, without taking the freedom to Examine their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions, or Judge whether they were ſquared according to the Word of God, or not; and that in caſe of diſobedience Excommunication was Juſt. That it was preciſely what the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> pretended, that it required nothing more. But that nevertheleſs when we have to do with her, we eſtabliſh a quite contrary Principle. That he deſired M. <hi>Claude</hi> to anſwer him diſtinctly to all this, and how he would liſten peacably to all he ſhould ſay to him. That as to the reſt, M. <hi>Claude</hi> ought to be ſo much the more ready to anſwer him in that there was nothing new in all this, and that the ſame <hi>Act</hi> and the ſame conſequences which he drew, were found in the Expoſition of the Catholick Doctrine.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Claude</hi> immediatly made anſwer, that tho he came not thither with any deſign to have a Regular Conference, yet nevertheleſs he was glad that this Occaſion furniſh'd him with the means of Teſtifying to M. <hi>de Condom</hi> the Eſteem he had for his Perſon, &amp; that not having any particular merit of his own, it was a great honour to him, to have ſuch a Prelate as M. <hi>de Condom</hi> to pick him out to meaſure himſelf with him. That he would endeavour to ſatisfy him upon all the points he had newly propoſed to him, and that if in the ſequel of the Diſcourſe, any Expreſſion ſhould ſtart from him, which might perſonally ſhock M. <hi>de Condom,</hi> he proteſted from that moment it ſhould be contrary to his intention.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>de Condom</hi> Replyed to this very handſome and very obliging things, and M. <hi>Claude</hi> renewing the Diſcourſe, told him, That in general, all he had newly alledged, concluded nothing leſs than blind and abſolute ſubmiſſion, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> pretended was owing to the deciſions of Eccleſiaſtical Aſſemblies. That a Diſtinction ought to be made of two ſorts of Authorities, the one Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign and Unlimited, to which one ought to pay a full and Entire Obedience, the other depending and Limited, which ought not to be obey'd, but under certain Conditions. That M. <hi>de Condom</hi> knew very well the Proteſtants did not attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute this firſt, but to God, alone ſpeaking in his holy Scriptures, and that for the other, they gave it to the Paſtors of the Church, Whether that they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered each a part, or were aſſembled in Synod or in Council. That their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority which is only Miniſterial, is Limited in two manners, whereof the one is, That they ought to make their deciſions, not of themſelves, as they think fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but according to the <hi>Word of God.</hi> The other that they leave ſtill to Perſons which are ſubmited to them the Right of Examining the Deciſions, to know if they are indeed Conformable to the <hi>Word of God:</hi> From whence it follows, That the Obedience which is owing them is Ever ſuſpendedly on this condition, That they have not deviated from the <hi>Word of God,</hi> That the Authority of the Paſtors &amp; of their Aſſemblies, cannot be greater than that of the Parliaments in <hi>France,</hi> which have not the Power to change the ancient Laws, nor of making new, and to whom, if it ſhould happen, that they ſhould order or exact things contrary to the Kings
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98072:4"/> Service, and the fidelity that is owing him, People would both have a Right, and be under an Obligation of diſobeying. That the Authority of Eccleſiaſtical Aſſemblies could not be greater than that of Fathers over Children, ſince both God and nature have inveſted Parents therewith, that Parents have a right of acting in the name of their Children; ſince they have the right of their education, the right of commanding them, and the Scripture in a thouſand places recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends to Children Docility and Obedience towards their Parents, but this does not hinder Children from having a right, or from being under an obligation of examining if what their Parents teach 'em, and what they command 'em be true or falſe, juſt or unjuſt. How that nevertheleſs it did not follow from thence but that the Authority of Paſtors and their aſſemblies was very great, as it did not follow but that of Parliaments, and that of parents, was likewiſe ſo, tho' they were limited authorities; that the Paſtors were as publick keepers of the Word of God, eſtabliſhed for the ſtudying it and meditating it inceſſantly in order to the drawing from thence truths neceſſary for the inſtruction of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and for the abridging private perſons of a trouble, to which they cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely apply themſelves, by reaſon of the diſtractions of Civil Affairs; that when the Paſtors acquited themſelves well of this duty, the people were obliged to receive their word with ſubmiſſion and obedience, but when they deviated from it, they were to look upon them as prevaricatours.</p>
            <p>Then deſcending particularly to the acts alledged by M. <hi>de Condom,</hi> he ſaid that 'twas upon this principle, and with theſe limitations, that we ought to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Clauſe of ſubmiſſion contained in the letter-miſſives to national ſynods, ſince it was only founded upon this ſuppoſition, that all will paſs therein according to the <hi>Word of God,</hi> for theſe terms, <hi>Being as we are perſwaded that God will preſide therein and conduct you by his Holy Spirit in all truth, by the rule of his Word,</hi> ſignify a perſwaſion of Charity and Equity, becauſe it is ever to be well preſumed of aſſemblies and hope that God will preſide therein, and that they will doe their duty untill the contrary appears. But that this did not carry ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute a ſubmiſſion, as to deprive people of the right of examining what ſhall be reſolved therein. As concerning the Act which condemneth the <hi>Independants,</hi> it is, (ſaid he) the higheſt juſtice. For tho the aſſemblies are not infallible, neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they ought not to be aboliſhed? 'Tis in truth an humane order, but however an order which God himſelf has eſtabliſhed for the conſervation of his Church, and from which one cannot depart without a crime. Nevertheleſs it does not follow from thence that a blind obedience is to be paid to the deciſſions of the aſſemblies, nor that it was the ſenſe of the Synod of <hi>Charenton.</hi> As for the deputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which the ſynod of <hi>Sainte Foy</hi> made of four perſons to go &amp; confer with thoſe of the confeſſion of <hi>Augſbourg,</hi> and to whom it gave a full power, you cannot draw from thence, ſaid he, any advantage. For it was with thoſe Deputies as with Ambaſſadours which the King ſends with full power to propoſe, treat and conclude as Plenipotentiaries which are ſent to negotiate the Peace. How full ſoever their power be, and tho' they are called Plenipotentiaries, the condition is always naturally underſtood, that they ſhall do nothing contrary to the true intereſt of their Authorizers, to whom what they do muſt neceſſarily revert for to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd and ratifyed without which nothing would de done, that they ought to be underſtood that full power given by the Synod to its Deputies, for the hearing of thoſe of the confeſſion of <hi>Augsbourg,</hi> for the receiving their propoſitions, their complaints, their overtures, to make the like to them reciprocally, to receive from them illuſtrations, and return the like, nay and to agree with them if poſſible, but not to be the abſolute Maſters of the Faith, nor to receive blindly all they ſhould have concluded; For in ſuch ſort of things the cauſe of recourſe to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorizers, and the neceſſity of ratification is naturally underſtood. To which M. <hi>Claude</hi> added this conſideration, that if the point in queſtion was the true ſenſe of an act of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, of a Canon, for example, of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98072:4"/> M. <hi>de Condom</hi> would doubtleſs find it more juſt, to receive it from him than from M. <hi>Claude,</hi> becauſe the thing in diſpute was the ſenſe of a Church whereof M. <hi>de Condom</hi> is a member, and that in all probability he ought to underſtand it better than a man that is not ſo. I expect then from you, My Lord Biſhop, ſaid he, the ſame equity, which if you'd receive from me the ſenſe of the Acts in diſpute, at leaſt unleſs the ſenſe I give 'em be contrary, to that of the Doctours of my communion, or evidently illuſory, or contrary to our other principles, but if the ſenſe I give of thoſe acts has nothing of that, methinks you have no right to reflect it, nor to fancy to your ſelf any other.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>de Condom</hi> renewing the Diſcourſe ſaid, that he would begin where M. <hi>Claude</hi> had ended, becauſe that he had ſaid in the laſt place, ſeem'd to have ſome juſtice and truth at firſt, tho' it had nothing at all of ſolidity. That what M. <hi>Claude</hi> ſaid would be true, if the point in iſſue was no more than explaining their rights and the manner or adminiſtring the Word, and the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in that he ſhould think him better informed, and that he did not at all intend to hinder him from explaning it as he pleas'd, the ſenſe of thoſe who had ſet up their diſcipline and made the acts he urg'd: That he knew they deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that they ought to ſubmit themſelves without examination, to the judgment of the Church. But that he pretended this abſolute ſubmiſſion was ſo neceſſary that thoſe very people who denyed it in ſpeculation, could not forbare eſtabliſhing it in practice, that thus they were fallen into a contradiction, and that 'twas what he pretended to prove, and wherein he was not obliged to beleive M. <hi>Claude.</hi> For if the thing in diſpute was to ſhow any contradiction in the ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church, he would not urge for authority it's explication, nor hinder M. <hi>Claude</hi> from drawing from the terms of the Councils ſuch concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as be thought fitting.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>de Condom</hi> making then pawſe, M. <hi>Claude</hi> reply'd, that ſince 'twas cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that thoſe who had made the acts in diſpute, deny'd that people ſhould ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelves without examination to the judgment of Eccleſiaſtical aſſemblies, he had at leaſt this advantage, that by M. <hi>de Condoms</hi> own confeſſion, the explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he gave to thoſe acts was conformable to the principles of the Proteſtants who had made them, and that it was much more reaſonable to receive it, than to fancy to one's ſelf a ſenſe which entangled 'em in a contradiction, that if the thing in diſpute was any act of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> he would make no diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty to receive the ſenſe which M. <hi>de Condom</hi> ſhould give thereof, conformable to the principles of that Church, unleſs the very words of the act ſhould oppoſe it, in which caſe he might induce the contradiction, and if M. <hi>de Condom</hi> was upon thoſe terms in regard of the acts alledged, it would be eaſy to ſee upon what terms he eſtabliſhed that pretended contradiction.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>de Condom</hi> ſaid how that was no difficult matter to make out: That he made it conſiſt in regard of the diſcipline, in that on the one ſide it required that the deciſion of the Doctrine ſhould he made in the conſiſtory by the <hi>Word of God,</hi> that it alſo underſtood that it was performed in the provincial Synod by the <hi>Word of God,</hi> as well as in the national, and that on the other it requir'd that if they did not acquieſce to the deciſion of the conſiſtory, or to that of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Synod, things ſhould remain in the ſame ſtate until the national Synod, where it ſayes, <hi>ſhall be performed the entire and ultimate Reſolution by the</hi> Word of God, <hi>to which if they do not acquieſce they ſhall be retrenched from the Church.</hi> Which clearly ſhow'd that the acquieſcing which was required for the deciſion of the national was founded not upon the <hi>Word of God</hi> preciſely as ſuch, for the deciſion of the Conſiſtory and that of the ſynod of the province had been alſo made by the <hi>Word of God</hi> preciſely as ſuch, and nevertheleſs the appeal was allowed of. But that it was founded upon the <hi>Word of God,</hi> in as much as explained and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted by the laſt judgment of the Church, that is to ſay, upon its being
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98072:5"/> the laſt and final reſolution, and by conſequence upon the authority of the aſſembly conſidered in it ſelf: Now this is, ſaid he, a manifeſt contradiction to the principle which denyes the abſolute ſubmiſſion to the judgment of the Church, that this was confirmed by the diſcipline which did not order any Excommunication againſt thoſe who do not acquieſe in the deciſions of the conſiſtory, and of the provincial Synod, and yet ordained againſt thoſe who refuſe to obey thoſe of the National.</p>
            <p>The ſame thing, ſaid he, appears by that letter-miſſive to the national Synod. For how can we promiſe and ſware we will ſubmit to all that ſhall be reſolved therein, without ſuppoſing we ow to the Church an entire and abſolute ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion? Say that we ſubmit thereunto upon the perſwaſion we have that God will preſide therein by his Spirit and his Word, and upon this ſware, that is to ſay, that upon this perſwaſion is founded on, an expreſs promiſe that God will conduct, the laſt judgment of his Church, by his Holy Spirit after an infallible manner. Nay and this, ſaid he, appears in the act of the national Synod of <hi>Charenton,</hi> againſt the Independants, for the reaſon then and there alledged, That if their principle was ſuffered, there might be as many Religions as Pariſhes, concluded for the abſolute Obedience to the deciſions of the Synods, ſince if it was allow'd to particulars to examine the ultimate deciſions, not only then might be as many Religions as Pariſhes, but as many Religions as Perſons, and that by conſequence there would be no way to preſerve the Unity of the Faith, or the Unity of the Church.</p>
            <p>As for what concerns the Deputies which the ſynod of <hi>Sainte foy</hi> nominated to go and confer with thoſe of the confeſſion of <hi>Augsbourg,</hi> he ſaid he did faithfully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg that how full power ſoever the ſynod might have given them, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention however of the Synod was not that it ſhould depend of them to overturn all, or to put, if he durſt make uſe of that expreſſion, the Cellar in the Garret and the Garret in the Cellar, that he really beleived that the ſynod meant, that what they effected ſhould return to them, and that in ſuch ſort of things a Ratification is allwayes neceſſary. But that it was a very amazing thing, and to which M. <hi>Claude</hi> had not made any anſwer, that this ſynod had offered to inſert in the Confeſſion of the Faith what the Deputies concluded with the <hi>Lutherans.</hi> For this is making a doubt of the confeſſion of their faith, of which we were how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever told that it contain'd nought elſe than the pure <hi>Word of God,</hi> wherein no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was to be changed. D'ye think, ſaid he, one can change the articles of your confeſſion of Faith.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>de Condom</hi> having ceaſed ſpeaking, M. <hi>Claude</hi> ſaid that he would anſwer to all the points of that diſcourſe, and deſired him to afford him a peaceable au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Whereunto in the firſt place he ſaid, that M. <hi>de Condom</hi> does miſappre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the Article of the Diſciplines which bears that in caſe they do not acquieſce in the deciſion of the conſiſtory, nor in that of the provincial ſynod, <hi>things ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the ſame ſtate untill the National, where ſhall be taken the laſt and final re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution from the</hi> Word of God, <hi>to which thoſe who ſhall not acquieſce ſhall be retrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Church.</hi> For it is not ſaid, if either that the Deciſions of the conſiſtory, and of the provincial ſynod ought not to be made by the <hi>Word of God,</hi> in like manner with thoſe of the National, or that this Word has not an equal authority, whether that it be declared, either by the conſiſtory, or by the ſynod of the Province, or by the national ſynod, or that it be preciſely to it alone, in as much as ſuch that we ow an entire obedience. But this order, added he, was eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for two reaſons, very different from that which you have pretended, the one is that therein appearance, that the examination of the <hi>Word of God,</hi> upon the point of queſtion ſhall be made in the conſiſtory with leſs exactneſs, and light, than in a ſynod compoſed of all the Miniſters of a province, nay and with leſs light and exactneſs in a provincial then in a national ſynod, which is commonly ſound to be compoſed of all the moſt ſagacious and moſt able perſons in a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98072:5"/> The other Reaſon is, That People may have prepoſſeſſions againſt a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtory, which ſhall hinder 'em from liſtening to it with all due docility; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it will not be ſo in regard of a Provincial Synod, which will be look'd upon as leſs intereſſed, and more empty of Paſſions and perſonal Prepoſſeſſions, and by Conſequence they will hearken to it more peaceably. In ſhort, thoſe ſort of Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Paſſions and Intereſts having ſtill much leſs room in a National Synod, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of Perſons far diſtant, who aſſemble from all parts of the Kingdom, in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability People will not entertain any prejudice againſt them, and by conſequence will receive the Word of God from their mouth with more docility, and liſten to 'em in a better diſpoſition. He ſaid then that this order had been taken for the avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as much as poſſible, two inconveniences; the one, That the final Deciſion might not be made lightly, inconſiderately, out of paſſion, and a humane Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt: The other, That the prepoſſeſſions againſt the perſons might not be an <hi>Obſtacle</hi> in the Parties to give Ear to, and receive the Word of God with Obedience and Submiſſion of Faith, which is owing it. But that from thence it could not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that in the ſenſe of the Diſcipline, it was not alwayes according to the Word of God, in as much as ſuch, and not to the authority of the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> that the Obedience ought to be rendred. That as to the Reſt, the Deciſion of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional was called Ultimate and Final, becauſe that in the humane Order, and in the preſent ſtate of things there was no going further.</p>
            <p>As for the Letter-miſſive to the National Synods, he made anſwer, That it did no more Conclude the abſolute Submiſſion, that the Act of the Diſcipline, ſince that the Condition of Judging according to the Word of God, was therein ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by theſe Terms, <hi>Being perſuaded as we are, that God will Preſide therein, by his Spirit, and his Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the reaſon alledged by the Synod of <hi>Charenton</hi> againſt the Independants, he ſaid, That it did not ſuppoſe a blind Obedience. That the Dependance which particular Churches have of Coloquies and Synods, is an Exteriour Order, which tho' it does not contain an Exteriour and infallible Means, to preſerve the Church in the Unity of the Faith, does not fail nevertheleſs to be of very great uſe for that very purpoſe, and that it is ever to be preſumed that the Bleſſing of God will accompany it, ſince it is an Order which he himſelf has Eſtabliſhed. That the Independants, who reject this Order, deprive themſelves of this means, and expoſe themſelves willingly to that inconvenience, of having as many Religions as Pariſhes, inſomuch that the Synod had reaſon to make them this Reproach. That there is no ſaying of the ſame thing of the Principle of the Proteſtants, which by rejecting the Blind Obedience, and abſolute Submiſſion, does nevertheleſs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the outward means uſeful and proper for the maintaining the Unity of the Faith. And as to what M. <hi>de Condom</hi> has ſaid, That without the abſolute Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, there might happen to be as many Religions as Pariſhes, he owns it might ſo happen humanly ſpeaking, notwithſtanding the practice of the order, and Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Aſſemblies,</hi> for humane Wit is of it ſelf ſubject to an infinite number of Errors. But that this cannot happen if a regard be had to God, who Bleſſing the outward order, and communicating to his truly Faithful and Elect, one and the ſame Spirit, maintains them by that means certain and infallible, in the Unity of one and the ſame Faith, and by conſequence in that of one and the ſame Church, That the Faith being a thing not humane but Divine, there is but one God alone, who can produce it, or who can preſerve it in the hearts of men. And this is alſo what he infallibly does in the hearts of his Elect, by his Spirit, and by the outward means of the Miniſtry, which he himſelf has eſtabliſhed, <hi>for</hi> Paul <hi>plants, and</hi> Apollo <hi>waters, but God only gives the Increaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then he proceeded to the Deputies which the Synod of <hi>Sainte Foy</hi> nominated to go to the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and ſaid, that he very agreeably received the Confeſſion which M. <hi>de Condom</hi> had newly made, <hi>That they meant not to give them the power of putting the Cellar in the Garret, and the Garret in the Cellar,</hi> as he had expreſſed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98072:6"/> himſelf after a very ingenious manner, and that a Return was required to the <hi>Authorizers,</hi> and a Ratification: That he thanked him very heartily for this down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Confeſſion, which in this reſpect decided the Queſtion, ſo as he could no longer make uſe of that <hi>Act</hi> for the blind obedience, which he pretended. That as to the reſt, his accuſation againſt that Synod, for having undertook to change the Confeſſion of the Faith, was null in the ſenſe which M. <hi>de Condom</hi> underſtood it? For that we ought to diſtinguiſh in the Confeſſion, what is Eſſential, from what is not ſo. That the Eſſential conſiſts in thoſe very things, which are called Articles, or Points of Faith, and what is not ſo, conſiſts in the terms and in the manners of expreſſion. That the Synod might well have conſented to a change of the expreſſions of the Confeſſion, nay, and to the inſerting therein of illuſtrations or explications if it was found uſeful for the bringing back Spirits that were gone aſtray, but that it never pretended that any thing ſhould be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the eſſential of that confeſſion, which in this regard remains immutable, for as much as it is Conformable to the <hi>Word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M. <hi>Claude</hi> having made an end, M. <hi>de Condom</hi> replyed, firſt of all, that what M. <hi>Claude</hi> had newly ſaid touching the order ſet down by the Diſcipline, did hot hinder but that the Diſcipline did order that thoſe who ſhould not acquieſce in the National Synod, ſhould be retrenched, that they did in effect retrench the <hi>Arminians</hi> in the Synod of <hi>Dordrect,</hi> and he asked M. <hi>Claude</hi> if he did not think that retrenchment juſt and legitimate? M. <hi>Claude</hi> having made anſwer, that he thought that what the Synod of <hi>Dordrect</hi> had done was very juſt: M. <hi>de Condom</hi> ſaid, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> demanded nothing more; that it acknowledged it ſelf obliged to judge according to the <hi>Word of God,</hi> and that was not in queſtion, but the point in iſſue was only the ſenſe and explication of that Word, and that it belonged to the Church to give that explication, to particular perſons to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce therein, and when in caſe they did not do it, the Church did juſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate. And thus it was that the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> had been excommunicated in the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the Letter-miſſive to National Synods is it not, ſaid he, a manifeſt illuſion to ſwear that they will ſubmit themſelves thereunto, ſuppoſed or upon condition that what ſhall be decided therein, ſhall be conformable to the <hi>Word of God?</hi> there's nothing ſerious in that: What ſay you Sir, to this? M. <hi>Claude</hi> ſaid there was no illuſion therein, and how he ſaw nothing but what was regular. If I comprehend your Doctrine aright, replyed M. <hi>de Condom,</hi> you believe a private perſon may doubt of the judgment of the Church even when it pronounces in its higheſt Tribunal. We beleive ſaid, M. <hi>Claude,</hi> that there's no certainty of faith that an Eccleſiaſtical Aſſembly ſhall judge rightly, and in that reſpect one may doubt thereof: But that nevertheleſs one ought ever to preſume well of an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and in that reſpect a body ought not to ſay he doubts it, but muſt ſay he hopes, nay and beleives it wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> judge well: For <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> has promis'd that all thoſe who ſeek ſhall find, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. and that it is to be preſumed they will do their duty in ſeeking well untill the Contrary appears. Wherefore this is an aſſurance of Charity and of Equity which excludes doubt in ſome ſenſe. But when people ſee Cabals, Factions, and humane intereſts to ſwarm and reign in Aſſemblies, then the truth is they may with reaſon doubt; for we ſee perſons who ſtray from their Duty, and by conſequence are not in a ſtate of hoping any thing from the bleſſing of God. I beſeech you, Sir, ſaid then M. <hi>de Condom,</hi> let us lay aſide what is only good to caſt duſt into the eyes. What you have newly ſtarted of Cabals, Factions and Intereſts, is impertinent and ſerves only to puzzle. I ask you, ſuppoſe there appears in an aſſembly neither Factions, Cabals nor In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, and that all its proceedings were juſt and regular, ought their deciſions to be received without examination? No, Sir, ſaid M. <hi>Claude.</hi> I had then reaſon, ſaid he, to ſay that all you have urg'd of Factions and Cabals is impertinent. Your concluſion's not juſt, reply'd M. <hi>Claude,</hi> for tho' there's nothing which ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers the preſumption, which people have that this aſſembly will do its Duty,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98072:6"/> and according to all appearances things will be orderly therein; this is however but a humane preſumption, which offers no certainty of Faith, and by conſequence does not hinder examination. But when diſorder and corruption are ſeen to reign therein, the preſumption is ſtill no longer in favour of ſuch an Aſſembly, and inſtead of entertaining good hopes of it, all is to be feared. Thus it is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon that I have ſpoke of Cabals and of Faction. There M. <hi>de Condom</hi> taking again in hand the thread of his diſcourſe, ſaid it was not true that the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants did abſolutely reject all ſorts of Eccleſiaſtical Aſſemblies, for they held one, ſaid he, at <hi>London</hi> in the Year 1653. ſo as the Synod of <hi>Charenton</hi> could not condemn them for that, but only becauſe they would not acknowledge there was owing a Dependance and an abſolute ſubmiſſion to the Synods.</p>
            <p>As for the Synod of <hi>Sainte Foy,</hi> added he, if the queſtion had been only to make illuſtrations and explications, as M. <hi>Claude</hi> call'd it, what neceſſity was there of inſerting them in the Confeſſion of the Faith? might it not have been done by an Act of Synod, without chewing the confeſſion? Wherefore its certain their deſign was to expreſs the Article of Faith touching <hi>the Lords Supper,</hi> in ambiguous terms, whereof both partyes had agreed, and which each might wrreſt to his advantage, a thing which had been attempted ſeveral times, but had not ſucceeded. Now this had been in effect not meerly giving illuſtrations and explications, nor even eſtabliſhing a Mutual Toleration, but changing the Confeſſion of the Faith. After that, added he, every one may gueſs what he ought to beleive of a Confeſſion of Faith, which a whole National Synod was willing to change. That as for the reſt, things were already in ſuch a point between M. <hi>Claude</hi> and him, that the truth muſt quickly appear, on the one ſide or the other. That the Principle which M. <hi>Claude</hi> maintained was a Principle of <hi>Inſupportable pride and preſumption.</hi> For is it not the higheſt arrogance for meer par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars to imagine they have more ſenſe for the underſtanding of the Scriptures, than a <hi>Whole Eccleſiaſtical Aſſembly, than a whole Council,</hi> Which was nevertheleſs what did neceſſarily follow from his Opinion, which gave particulars the right and freedom of examining what the Councils have decided, that there was a great deal more <hi>Chriſtian Juſtice and Humility in ſubmitting ones ſelf abſolutely to the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, &amp; pay them abſolute obedience,</hi> than <hi>to pretend to reform its Deciſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M. <hi>Claude's</hi> Turn being to ſpeak, ſaid how 'twas true that their Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, did mention that after the laſt and final reſolution which ſhould be made by <hi>the Word of God in the aſſembly of a National Synod, thoſe who ſhould refuſe to acquieſce ſhould be excommunicated, but that the Diſcipline did in no wiſe mean that they were to acquieſce to the authority of the Aſſembly preciſely,</hi> but as he had already ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it, <hi>to the authority of the Word of God;</hi> according to which the <hi>Aſſembly was to ſquare the deciſion, which ſtill ſuppoſes an examination, that thus the excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication was juſt upon this ſuppoſition that the Word of God had been followed, and not otherwiſe. That indeed the excommunications of Councils were neither juſt nor efficacious but when their deciſions were grounded upon this Word, and if they were not, their excommunications where unjuſt, &amp; fell again with full right upon the head of thoſe who had utter'd them:</hi> according to the Maxime of St. <hi>Paul, If we ourſelves or an Angel from Heaven ſhould preach to you beſides what we have preached to you, let him be accurſed.</hi> That if the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> pretended only that, they would not diſpute with her, becauſe any one would ſtill have a right &amp; an obligation to examine if the Deciſions are conformable or not to the <hi>Word of God,</hi> and by conſequence whether the excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications are juſt or unjuſt. That in this Spirit it was, that the Synod of <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drecht</hi> had condemned, not the perſons againſt whom they did not pronounce any <hi>Anathema,</hi> but the errors, by ſhewing them contrary to the expreſs Texts of Scripture. That for his own part he held that excommunication very legitimate, but 'twas becauſe he ſaw it grounded upon the Scripture, and not upon the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Aſſembly.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Independants</hi> had in truth held an extraordinary Aſſembly in 1653. to draw up their Confeſſion of Faith but this did not hinder but that commonly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98072:7"/> they rejected the uſe of Colloquies and Synods; and for that reaſon was it the Synod of <hi>Charenton</hi> had condemned them, and not for their not having rendred to Aſſemblies a blind and abſolute obedience in matter of Faith, as appears by the very Act.</p>
            <p>As to the Synod of <hi>Sainte Foy,</hi> I know not, ſaid my Lord, why you will needs have it there was a deſign to change the Confeſſion of the Faith, in what it has eſſential, for this is in no wiſe in the power of National Synods, and if that of <hi>Sainte Foy</hi> had undertaken it, it had been diſown'd by all the Proteſtants of the Kingdom. I own they might put Illuſtrations and Explications in an Act, but you muſt alſo own to me that they could do it in the confeſſion, and when a thing may be done by ſeveral ways, People are at liberty to chuſe that which ſeems the moſt proper. There M. <hi>de Condom</hi> interrupting M. <hi>Claude,</hi> ſaid, how it was certain this Synod was contriving how to couch the Article of the Lords Supper in ambiguous terms, and that it was the deſign of the Mediators, that there was mention made of deciding every point of doctrine which did ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly regard the reality which the <hi>Lutherans</hi> held. M. <hi>Claude</hi> made anſwer, that to impute to the Synod a deſign of agreeing upon ambiguous terms, was one of the conjectures of M. <hi>de Condom,</hi> whereof he had not any proof, and for his part he conjectur'd otherwiſe, that he did not doubt but the deſign of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod was to do what was poſſible to bring the <hi>Lutherans</hi> to a full knowledge of the truth, and this was that which ſignified that full power of deciding with them every point of Doctrine, namely by the Word of God.</p>
            <p>Then falling again to the thread of his diſcourſe he made anſwer to that M. <hi>de Condom</hi> had ſaid, that it was an inſupportable pride for meer particulars to believe they have more ſenſe for the underſtanding of the Scripture, than a whole Eccleſiaſtical Aſſembly; whereupon he ſaid, that indeed meer particulars ought not to preſume ſo much of themſelves as to believe they have more ſenſe for the underſtanding of the Scriptures than a whole Aſſembly; that on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry People ought to preſume well of an Aſſembly, and have docility for it. But that this did not hinder but that they ought nevertheleſs to have their eyes open to ſee if indeed an Aſſembly had done its Duty, after the example of the <hi>Bereans,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, that they conferred what St. <hi>Paul</hi> told there with the Scriptures to know if it was ſo; that we ought to diſtinguiſh a judgment of Charity and of Humility, which only fram'd a probable concluſion, from a perſwaſion of infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility, which fram'd a neceſſary concluſion, that out of this judgment of Charity and of Humility we ought to preſume in favour of an Aſſembly, and even of a particular Doctor, but that becauſe as well Aſſemblies as particular perſons are ſubject to error, we ought not to puſh on this judgment of Charity and Humility, even to the blinding ones ſelf, when that indeed an Aſſembly or a Doctor had err'd, and that this would be puſhing things beyond their juſt bounds; for example, ſaid he, being what I am in my flock, People are obliged to prejudge in my favour, that I underſtand better the ſenſe of the Scripture than meer private perſons, but they ought not nevertheleſs to think me infallible, nor imagine it can never happen to me to be deceived in point of Doctrine; in which caſe certain it is that a meer private perſon would have a right to believe he might underſtand the ſenſe of the Scripture, better than me. The buſineſs in diſpute, ſaid then M. <hi>de Condom,</hi> is not about particular Doctors, we know particular Doctors may err, and by conſequence, we ought not to have for them an abſolute obedience, but we talk of a whole body of Eccleſiaſtical Aſſemblies, and I require of you a clear anſwer upon this point, whether you believe meer par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons may underſtand the ſenſe of the Scripture better than a whole Body of the Church aſſembled in Council?</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Claude</hi> made anſwer, that he had ſpoke of particular Doctors only to ſhew that humility ought not to be abuſed, nor under a pretence of ſhunning pride and preſumption, make men blind themſelves; for if there be not an abſolute obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98072:7"/> owing to particular Doctors, as M. <hi>de Condom</hi> did aver it, there is then neither pride nor preſumption in believing it may ſo happen that one may underſtand the ſenſe of the Scripture better than them, tho' people are obliged to preſume Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably &amp; probably that this will not happen. That it was the ſame thing in regard of the Aſſemblies which not being of themſelves infallible, ought not to pretend to have an abſolute obedience paid them, being a thing which is only owing to God, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf had ſaid <hi>there was no dominion over the Faith of the</hi> Corinthians.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>de Condom</hi> ſaid this paſſage was ill alledged and ask'd M. <hi>Claude</hi> if he did not think an abſolute Obedience was owing to Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> M. <hi>Claude</hi> made anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer that an abſolute Obedience was owing to things divine which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> taught, and not to his perſon, neither is it ſaid M. <hi>de Condom</hi> to the perſons who compoſe the Councils we pretend that Obedience to be paid, but to the Holy Spirit which conducts 'em, according to what the Council of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſaid, it <hi>has pleas'd the Holy Spirit and us.</hi> When the Holy Spirit, ſaid M. <hi>Claude</hi> appears in the Deciſions of the Councils as it appeared in the Doctrine of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and in that of the Council of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> we ought to render them that Obedience, and not otherwiſe. Now it appears therein when their deciſions are framed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Word of God. M. <hi>de Condom</hi> inſiſted, there was no queſtion about the Word of God, but about the true ſenſe thereof. M. <hi>Claude</hi> ſaid t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is diſtinction was of no uſe, for the true ſenſe of the Word of God, and the Word of God are but one and the ſame thing.</p>
            <p>There M. <hi>de Condom</hi> return'd to the Independants, and ſaid, that upon the principle of M. <hi>Claude</hi> there was no way to avoid <hi>Independantiſme,</hi> nor prevent the being as many Religions as Pariſhes, as many Religions as heads. That the Independants did not reject the Aſſemblies, for inſtructions, but that they would not allow the Aſſemblies ſhould decide by authority, and that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended reformed were conformable to them. He repeated over and over the ſame thing a pretty while, to which M. <hi>Claude</hi> reparteed what he had already anſwered that in truth there was no humane means, certain and infallible to hinder the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of the with of man, but that there was one divine and infallible, which was the Holy Spirit which God communicated to his true Beleivers and that the Synods and other Aſſemblies were uſeful means, and proper for that purpoſe, and that the Independants had only been condemned, becauſe they rejected theſe laſt, and not becauſe they would not allow the Aſſemblies ſhould decide with an entire and abſolute authority, that tho' the Proteſtants did not allow Aſſemblies a ſoveraign and illimited authority, they allowed them however all the authority that Miniſters and the Diſpenſers of the Word of God can have.</p>
            <p>This would be diſputing everlaſtingly ſaid then M. <hi>de Condom,</hi> I ask you once again, Sir, if you believe meer particular Perſons can underſtand the ſenſe of the Word of God better than the whole Church Aſſembled in a Council. M. <hi>Claude</hi> ſaid he had already anſwered him to that, <hi>viz.</hi> that it did not commonly ſo happen, nay and that People were obliged to hope better from the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Aſſembly, but that it might nevertheleſs happen that humane paſſions and worldly intereſts prevailing in an Aſſembly, the Deciſions would not be ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red therein according to the truth. There's no having recourſe, ſaid M. <hi>de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> to humane paſſions, nor to worldly intereſts, you muſt anſwer in a word to the queſtion and ſay yes, or no. Humane paſſions and worldly intereſts, ſaid M. <hi>Claude,</hi> are very reaſonably urg'd upon this ſubject, for thoſe are the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal cauſes of erroneous Deciſions, but ſince you will not allow 'em to be ſpoken off to you, Ile anſwer you by diſtinguiſhing and ſaying, that God does not allow that this ordinarily happens, but that in abſolutely ſpeaking it may happen. M. <hi>de Condom</hi> ſaid he demanded but that, and how 'twas the greateſt of all abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities to beleive it may come to paſs a meer particular perſon may better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the ſenſe of the Scripture better than a whole Church Aſſembled in Council.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:98072:8"/>
            <p>M. <hi>Claude</hi> made anſwer, how he wondered he ſhould tax us of ſo great an abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, what was but an effect of the freedom of God in the diſpenſation of his Grace. That if the point was concerning humane Lights, there would be abſurdity in ſaying that a meer particular perſon, had more underſtanding than a whole Aſſembly, and that this would be a principle of pride and preſumption. But tho the thing in iſſue was the Lights of the Holy Spirit which breathes where it pleaſes, and which God may poſſibly not give to a whole Aſſembly, when he ſhall give it to meer particular perſons, that this ſame thing had effectually hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the time of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> according to what he himſelf had ſaid in <hi>Matt. I give thee, thanks, O Father, Lord of Heaven and Earth, for that thou haſt concealed thoſe things from the Wiſe and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, and haſt revealed them to the little.</hi> That the whole <hi>Judaick</hi> Church had determined in its Aſſemblies that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> was an impoſtour. That it was nevertheleſs not only a Church, out the only Church in the world, inveſted with all the authority of God, who had founded, nouriſhed and brought it up untill that time, that God had inſtructed it by his Apoſtles, had made in the depoſitary of his Oracles. That with a juſt Title it gloryed in a ſucceſſion of two thouſand years, that its Aſſemblies were in the former, and <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> Himſelf own'd it, <hi>they are ſeated,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>in the Chair of</hi> Moſes, <hi>all the things they ſhall bid you keep, keep them and do them.</hi> That never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs this Church had determined the moſt Capital and moſt Criminal of all Errours, which was to reject <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> as a wretched perſon and an impoſtour that then it muſt neceſſarily have been ſaid, that meer particular perſons might better underſtand the ſenſe of the Scripture, than the whole Body of the Church Aſſembled, and that if the principle of M. <hi>de Condom</hi> was true, namely, that one muſt have an abſolute ſubmiſſion for the Deciſions of Eccleſiaſtical Aſſemblies without attributing to ones ſelf the right examining 'em, it would be to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and all thoſe who ſhould beleive in him. For according to this Principle <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ought not to addreſs himſelf to the People after the Deciſions of the Church which were contrary to him, neither ought the People to have given ear to him, ſince they were no longer allow'd to examine what had been decided, nevertheleſs, added he, I. C. did not forbare preaching to the People, and converting ſeveral, the People alſo liſtened to his motion notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Deciſions that were againſt him, for whence it follows that his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Blind Obedience is bad, and contrary to the conduct of I. C. and that of his diſcipline.</p>
            <p>That 'twould be to no purpoſe to urge that I. C. made uſe of miracles by which he prov'd his Authority Divine; for there are two ſorts of micracles, the one true, the other falſe, the one for lying the other for truth. God Himſelf has made this diſtinction in the third Chap. of <hi>Deut.</hi> Where he ſayes to the <hi>Iſraelites, that if a Prophet does miracles and turns them afterwards to other Gods, they ought not to listen to him becauſe it is God who tryes them.</hi> I. C. himſelf and acknowledged the truth of this diſtinction. If then, ſaid he, the Principle of M. <hi>de Condom</hi> had held good, it could not have been in the People to have made that judgment after the Church had decided <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> performed his miracles not by the vertue of God but by that of <hi>Belezbub,</hi> they might not after that, according to M. <hi>de Condom;</hi> opened their eyes to ſee thoſe miracles or receive the leaſt impreſſion of them, from whence it follows that this principle is falſe, and deſtructive to the Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>de Condom</hi> interrupted M. <hi>Claude</hi> upon this, and ſaid, that there was no doing of this example of the <hi>Judaiſh</hi> Church for ſaid he, the Synagogue was to fall, the Prophets hand ſo foretold it, and the people ought not by conſequence pay it ſuch an obedience as ought to be paid to the Church of <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> which is never to fall. To which M. <hi>Claude</hi> reparteed, that ſince the Synagogue was to fall, it might ſo happen that meer particular perſons underſtood better the ſenſe of the Scripture than a whole Body of the Church in its Aſſemblies,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98072:8"/> which was the point in iſſue, and how from thence it plainly followed, 'twas nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pride nor preſumption in particular perſons to be believed it might ſo befall 'em as to underſtand the Scripture better than a whole Body of Aſſembly, or to examine its deciſions upon this Principle. That he required nothing more.</p>
            <p>Beſides this Reaſon, ſaid he could not have any effect upon the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> People becauſe that not only the <hi>Synagogue</hi> were not agreed upon the point, but on the contrary maintaining <hi>that it was never to fall,</hi> and produced in favour of its ſelf promiſes which at firſt puſh ſeemed extreamly ſtrong: To alledge upon this the prophets who foretold its fall, would be nothing to the purpoſe, for the buſineſs in Diſpute is <hi>the ſenſe of thoſe Propheſies,</hi> and the <hi>Synagogue</hi> explaining them in a ſenſe which was favourable to it, 'twas the People's duty, according to the principle of M. <hi>de Condom</hi> to ſtick to that explication without examining it; in ſhort ſaid he, this fall of the <hi>Synagogue makes not any difference between it's Aſſemblies and thoſe of the Chriſtian Church, for the Queſtion in diſpute for what promiſes ſoever of Perpetual ſubſiſtence the Church of Jeſus Chriſt has, there is nothing in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which aſſures us the Aſſemblies of Councils ſhall not fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There M. <hi>de Condom</hi> taking up the Diſcourſe ſaid, how what M. <hi>Claude</hi> ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the time of the fall of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ynagogue</hi> was of all thing in the world the moſt unſeaſonable, for then there would not be ſaid <hi>that there was no viſible authority upon Earth,</hi> wherein people ought, neceſſarily to acquieſce, <hi>ſince</hi> I. C. <hi>himſelf was there</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>the truth it ſelf appeared viſibly among men, to who God had rendred Teſtimony from Heaven, and who performed miracles.</hi> D'you, added he, but bring us back, I. C. <hi>teaching, preaching, working of miracles,</hi> and we ſhall have no more nee of the <hi>Authority</hi> of the Church. What I have urg'd, ſaid M. <hi>Claude,</hi> is not only the thing in the world the moſt part, but the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aineſt and moſt concluding, and I hope you your ſelf will agree to 'em when I ſhall have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired you to conſider <hi>how this viſible Authority of the Son of God,</hi> was then the point in queſtion be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>een the Synagogue and I. C. how it was this point which the <hi>Synagogue</hi> had decided in the negative, that the buſineſs was to know if I C. was an <hi>Impoſtour,</hi> or not, if his <hi>miracles</hi> were from <hi>God</hi> or from <hi>Belzebub,</hi> that the <hi>viſible Authority</hi> of I. C. could not decide the queſtion in the Spirit of the People; for an Authority does decide nothing untill firſt of all it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e received, and that of I. C. was not ſo yet, ſince the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pute was about receiving, or rejecting it: thus there only remain'd the authority of the Church which had decided againſt him, from whence it follows, <hi>that according to the principle of</hi> M. <hi>de Condom parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons ought to have ſtuck to that and recieve Jeſus Christ.</hi> M. <hi>de Condom</hi> called this argument of M. <hi>Claudes</hi> a <hi>Jewiſh argument.</hi> M. <hi>Claude</hi> replyed that it was not his argument, he ought to call <hi>Jewiſh</hi> argument ſince it concluded in favour of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> but that it was the contrary principle which he ought to call by that name, ſince it favored the cauſe of the <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this M. <hi>Claude</hi> ſaid that if he would have recourſe to Hiſtory it would be no difficult matter for him to ſhow how ſeveral Councils fell, and have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided the errors as amongſt others the Council of <hi>Arimini</hi> which condemned the <hi>Conſubſtantiation of the Son,</hi> that is to ſay <hi>His Eternal Divinity,</hi> M. <hi>de Condom</hi> cryed out, whither d'you hurry us to the Council of <hi>Arimini,</hi> when ſhall we have done if we muſt diſcuſs all thoſe hiſtories? D'you not know that the Council of <hi>Arimini</hi> was an Aſſembly of robbers, that my Lord ſaid M. <hi>Claude,</hi> is juſt what I would ſay, <hi>that a General Council</hi> may become an Aſſemby of robbers, now here's one compoſed of four hundred Biſhops, what is become of it, M. <hi>de Condom</hi> ſaid that the Biſhops had been forced by the Authority of the Emperor, who had ſent Souldiers thither; but that afterwards being return'd every one to his home they had diſown'd what they had done, and had ſhewn repentance for it, M. <hi>Claude</hi> replyed that in truth ſeveral of them had acknowledged their fault, but that this very Act of their acknowledging it and repenting it, as M. <hi>de Condom</hi> does affirm, confirms this truth, <hi>that they had committed it</hi> and there's no need
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98072:9"/> of knowing out of what principle they had committed it, ſince they had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted it in reality; that their Recantation alſo ſhewed that each of them in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular thought not himſelf obliged to acquieſce in what they had determined all together in Council.</p>
            <p>M <hi>de Condom</hi> cryed out, 'twas not neceſſary to enter into all thoſe points of hiſtory which would lead 'em too far. The thing, ſaid he, may more eaſily be decided: the Diſpute is concerning <hi>the firſt principle of the faith of particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which you beleive to be the Holy writ, and we the authority of the</hi> Church. I ſuppoſe a Child that has been baptized, and has not yet read the Scripture, and I ask you by what principle that Child beleives the Scripture to be <hi>Divine,</hi> that the Book of Canticles, for Example, where there's not a <hi>Word ſpoke of God is divine. Either that child that's a</hi> Chriſtian, <hi>who has received the Holy Spirit and the Faith infuſed by Baptiſm and is a member of the</hi> Church, <hi>doubts of the Divinity of the Scripture, or does not doubt of it, if not he beleives it then Divine by the Authority of the</hi> Catholick Church, <hi>which is the first Authority, under which he lives; if he doubts of it, a</hi> Chriſtian <hi>may then doubt of the truth of the Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M. <hi>Claude</hi> made anſwer that he might have ſomething to ſay upon M. <hi>de Condoms</hi> ſuppoſing that every child baptized, received the Holy Spirit, but that he would not inſiſt upon what is ſpoken by the by, nor deviate from the principal ſubject in queſtion, wherefore he'd be contented with making ſome reflections upon what M. <hi>de Condom</hi> had juſt urg'd. The firſt ſaid he ſhall be that probably the firſt knowledge which the Holy Spirit gives to the Child of the Catholick Church, is by his Creed, wherein he ſays, <hi>Credo Sanctam Eccleſiam Catholicam.</hi> Never theleſs in the Creed this Article is poſteriour to the Articles of Doctrine ſince it begins with <hi>God the Father Almighty,</hi> and continues with <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and with the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> after which comes the <hi>Catholick Church.</hi> Now it appears clearly from thence that Faith of the Doctrine does not depend on the Authority of the Church, for otherwiſe the ſymbole muſt have been compos'd after an other manner, and ſay at firſt, <hi>I beleive the</hi> Catholick Church, <hi>and by the</hi> Catholick Church <hi>I beleive in God the Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>My ſecond Reflection, ſaid he, is that you cannot ſuppoſe as you do, that firſt authority under which the Child begins to live is that of the Catholick Church, for certain it is that the firſt Authority under which a Child lives, is that of his Father, or that of his Mother, or if you will that of his nurſe, and how that of the Church can only come afterwards, and in ſome ſort by dependance on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other. Now from thence it follows that this firſt Authority which is the Paterna may as well conduct the Child to the Scripture as to the Church.</p>
            <p>In the third place, ſaid he, there is nothing more eaſy then to retort your argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt your ſelf: Either the Child Baptized doubts of the Authority of the Church or does not doubt of it, if he does not doubt of it, he beleives it then by the authority of the Scripture, for he cannot by any other way beleive it of Divine Faith, and by conſequence it is not the Church which makes us beleive Scripture, but it is the Scripture which makes beleive the Church, which is that, we aim at. If he doubts of it, ſee here then a Chriſtian who has received the Holy Spirit and Faith infuſed by Baptiſme, and who is a member of the Church who can doubt of the firſt authority, on which depends the reſt of the Faith. That the Child cannot beleive of Divine Faith the Authority of the Church but by that of the Scripture, I prove it, for if it is not by the Scripture that he beleives the Church and its authority it is then either by way of inſpiration and enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſm, or by the Authority of his Father, of his Mother, or of his nurſe, or by ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument drawn out of the very Nature of the Church. It cannot be out of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſme for the Holy Spirit does not act in that manner. Neither can it be by the Authority of the Father, or the Mother, or Nurſe, for you ſee this would be to eſtabliſh thoſe ſorts of authorities for the firſt principle of Faith, neither can
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98072:9"/> it be by proof and arguments drawn out of the very nature of the Church; for as in your argument you ſuppoſe the Child has not yet <hi>read the Scripture,</hi> I ſuppoſe alſo in mine that he has not yet <hi>Meditated upon the Nature of the</hi> Catholick Church, and knows <hi>only its name.</hi> It then remains that the Child believes the Catholick Church by <hi>Scripture,</hi> which is, what you do not allow off, or does not beleive it at all, and that he doubts it, which is the ſame inconvenience you would have thrown me in, in regard of the <hi>Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here a body may ſay with truth, that M. <hi>de Condoms Wit was not in its uſual ſtate, and how that freedom which is natural to it was ſenſibly diminiſh'd,</hi> He undertook to maintain that the firſt Authority under which a Child lived in <hi>reſpect of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> was that of the Catholick Church, and not that of the Father or Mother. M. <hi>Claude</hi> replyed, that there was no denying a thing ſo clear as that, that the firſt Authority in <hi>reſpect of Religion,</hi> is that of the Father or Mother, who took the firſt care of the Education of the Child, or that it was from them that the Child learnt the firſt time that there was a Catholick Church, to which he ought to <hi>range himſelf,</hi> or that there was a <hi>Scripture</hi> which was Divine, and to which he ought to <hi>ſubmit himſelf.</hi> Now the point being to know by what means the child might believe the Authority of the Catholick Church, he had only to chuſe either the way of <hi>Enthuſiaſm,</hi> or that of the <hi>Paternal Authority,</hi> or that of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which might inſtruct him. M. <hi>de Condom</hi> replyed, <hi>the faith of the child in the Authority of the Church was divine,</hi> becauſe <hi>'twas the Holy Spirit that formed it in him.</hi> M. <hi>Claude</hi> reparty'd that the thing in debate was not the cauſe efficient which produced that <hi>Faith in the child,</hi> but the argument by which it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced; that if M. <hi>de Condom</hi> underſtood that the <hi>Holy Ghoſt produced it in the child,</hi> without proof and without argument it would be a kind of <hi>Enthuſiaſm,</hi> and yet the <hi>Holy Ghost did not act in that manner.</hi> M. <hi>de Condom</hi> ſaid, that in effect there were <hi>Motives of credibility;</hi> to which M. <hi>Claude</hi> replyed, that if he gave the child time to examine the <hi>Motives of credibility</hi> by the Authority of the Church, and to perceive the force of 'em, he alſo would give the ſame child the time to examine the <hi>Motives of credibility</hi> for the Authority of the Scripture, and to perceive the force of them; and this being ſo, he muſt renounce his argument, which ſuppos'd the child as not yet having read the Scripture.</p>
            <p>But is it not true, ſaid M. <hi>de Condom,</hi> that in this ſtate either the child doubts or does not doubt of the <hi>Divinity of the Scriptures?</hi> But ſaid M. <hi>Claude,</hi> is it not true that in that ſtate either the child doubts or does not doubt of the authority of the Church? for if you ſuppoſe the child before his having read the Scripture, I ſuppoſe him alſo before his having read the <hi>Motives of credibility</hi> for the authority of the Church. You are obliged to anſwer to my argument, and the ſame anſwer you ſhall make me, I ſhall make you; you may take what courſe you pleaſe, but i'le be ſure to anſwer you directly to your reaſoning: now the child muſt be diſtinguiſh'd in three times; before his father has ſhew'd him the Bible, and told him that this Book is Divine, after his Father has told him ſo, without his having yet read it him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, after he has read it himſelf. At the firſt time, which is that wherein you conſider him in your argument, there's no ſaying he doubts, or does not doubt, for neither the one nor the other is true in the ſenſe you underſtand it. Not to doubt of a thing ſignifies to be aſſured of it. Now before a body can ſay, either that one doubts, or is aſſured of the Quality of a thing, one muſt know the thing it ſelf. I do not doubt nor am I aſſured that ſuch a perſon is the King of <hi>Spain</hi> until firſt I have had ſome knowledg of the Perſon. Wherefore your argument is not juſt, either the child doubts or does not doubt of the divinity of the Scripture, there's a <hi>Medium,</hi> namely which is called an <hi>ignorance of pure negation.</hi> He knows not yet what Scripture is, never having heard talk of it. To doubt or not to doubt of the divinity of the Scripture, a man muſt have ſome knowledg of it, and frame to himſelf ſome idea at leaſt of it. But the child does not frame to it any idea of a Book, whereof he never heard any mention; in the ſecond time when his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98072:10"/> Father has ſhewed him the Bible, and told him this <hi>Book is is the word of God,</hi> yet without his having yet read it himſelf, He beleives it <hi>the Word of God:</hi> He beleives it the <hi>Word of God,</hi> not of <hi>Divine Faith,</hi> but of <hi>Humane Faith,</hi> becauſe his Father told him ſo, which is a ſtate of <hi>Catechumene.</hi> In the third time when he has read himſelf this Book, and perceives the <hi>Efficaciouſneſs</hi> of it, he believes it <hi>the Word of God</hi> no longer by <hi>Humane Faith,</hi> becauſe his Father has told him ſo, but by <hi>Divine Faith,</hi> becauſe he himſelf has immediately perceived the <hi>Divinity</hi> of it, and it is the <hi>ſtate of the faithful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M. <hi>de Condom</hi> faſtned upon this word <hi>Catechumene,</hi> and ſaid that the child was a Chriſtian, was baptized, and was in the <hi>Allyance of God.</hi> M. <hi>Claude</hi> made anſwer, that by the word <hi>Catechumene</hi> he meant only, the child baptized, in the ſtate he received the firſt inſtructions. M. <hi>de Condom</hi> repeated again much the ſame things he had ſaid, ſtill affirming 'twas by the <hi>authority of the</hi> Church that the child received the <hi>Scriptures as Divine,</hi> and after having received them from the Church as Divine, he received alſo from the Church their ſenſe and interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p>Tell me, I beſeech your Lordſhip, ſaid then M. <hi>Claude,</hi> When a Child learns the firſt time, there is a Catholick Church, is it ſimply a general Idea, which only conſiſts in knowing there is a Catholick Church, without knowing where it is, or what it is: Or does it determine that Church, whoſe Aſſemblies it ſees? For if it be the firſt, it is a principle of Faith very inſignificant, very uſeleſs, which you eſtabliſh. I know there is a Catholick Church to whoſe authority People ought to ſubmit themſelves, but I know not where it is, or what it is, this would be a ſtrange principle of Faith. True, ſaid M. <hi>de Condom,</hi> the Child determines this Idea to that Church particularly whoſe Aſſemblies it ſees or aſſiſts at it ſelf, and beleives it to be the Catholick Church, and not ſimply there is one. Let us then ſuppoſe, ſaid M. <hi>Claude,</hi> a child born in a <hi>Heretick</hi> or <hi>Schiſmatick</hi> Church, in the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> Church for example, the firſt principle of Faith this child will entertain, will be that of the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> Church, as being the Catholick. It will be from it, and according to its authority, that he will receive the Scripture; as <hi>Divine,</hi> from it 'twill be he'll receive the ſence &amp; explication of that Scripture and he can never believe he has a right to examine the Deciſions of his <hi>Ethiopian</hi> Church, for fear of falling into the inconvenience of imagining he may better underſtand the ſenſe of the Scripture, he a meer particular perſon, than the whole Body of the Church. <hi>Tell me,</hi> My Lord, <hi>Whether by this principle the child will not always remain in that Heretical and Schiſmatical</hi> Church? <hi>Tell me by what way you pretend to free him out of it? Certain then it is, your Principle is equally proper to maintain the Jew in Judaiſme, the Pagan in Paganiſm, the Hereticke in Hereſy, as the Orthodox in the true</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>de Condom</hi> replied to this, that one was to diſtinguiſh in the perſuaſion of the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> child what came from the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> from what came by humane prepoſſeſſion; that 'twas the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> which dictated to him in general there was a Catholick Church in what place ſoever it was, but that this Catholick Church was that where he was born, this came from humane prepoſſeſſion. That in truth he received the Scripture from the hand of that Church, and did not believe it divine but by its authority, but afterwards by reading the Scripture, <hi>the Holy Spirit produced in him doubts againſt the Church of his Birth, and from that means freed him from the Hereſy, and the Schiſm wherein he was engaged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M. <hi>Claude</hi> made anſwer, that either M. <hi>de Condom</hi> muſt renounce his principle, or own the impoſſibility of what he urg'd, For ſince this <hi>Ethiopian</hi> in diſpute cannot nor ought not to underſtand the Scripture, but in the ſenſe of the Church, by the authority of which he beleives it divine, and from whoſe hand he receives it's interpretation, it is impoſſible that by reading the Scripture there ſhould ariſe any doubts in his mind, contrary to the truth of his Church; for he only explains that Scripture conformably to the ſenſe of that Church. But if on the contrary,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98072:10"/> you mean this man ſhould explain of himſelf the Scripture, and takes it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n an other ſenſe than his Church does, you make him, ſaid he, renounce your princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, for which you have hitherto combated, and you not only make him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce it, but you eſtabliſh that it is the Holy Spirit himſelf which makes him renounce it, and all the inconveniences which you have ſo exaggerated, vaniſh into ſmoak; he added, that what M. <hi>de Condom</hi> had juſt ſaid, juſtified the proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, for tho' it were it which we ought to have beleived from our birth to have been the Catholick Church, tho' it were by it and its authority that we ſhould have received the Scripture as divine, we cannot be blamed for having diſtinguiſh'd in that Beleif, what was of the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> from what proceeded from <hi>humane prepoſſeſſion, We cannot be blamed for having in reading the Scripture, received doubts contrary to the truth of that Church, and for having freed our ſelves by that means from out of its communion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M. <hi>de Condom</hi> ſaid, there was this difference, that the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> withdrawing from out his Church, would joyn himſelf to the Catholick, whereas the pretended reformed have not joyned themſelves to any communion, you ſought ſtrongly after that, ſaid he, of <hi>Jeremy</hi> the Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> but he would have nothing to do with you. We did not ſeparate of our ſelves, ſaid M. <hi>Claude;</hi> and this is ſufficient to ſay that we did not ſeparate our ſelves from the true Church, If <hi>Jeremy</hi> the <hi>Patriarch</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> would not accept of us as you ſay, it is to his own, he did not what he ought.</p>
            <p>Upon this the Company got up, and the Converſation, which continued ſtill ſome time, became much more confuſed. There was ſpoken therein of diverſe things. M. <hi>de Condom</hi> compared with a great deal of exaggeration, <hi>the ſeparation of the Proteſtants</hi> to that of the ancient <hi>Hereticks,</hi> to that of the <hi>Arrians,</hi> and to that of the <hi>Macedonians, who had made new</hi> Churches. M. <hi>Claude</hi> compared the conduct of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to that of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> of I. C. when they were <hi>ſeparated from the Jews,</hi> and ſaid that as the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſupported themſelves upon the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> who ſupported themſelves upon the authority of <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Aſſemblyes,</hi> the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> did the like againſt the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> He ſaid the <hi>Arrians</hi> maintained <hi>that the conſubſtantiality of the Son of God,</hi> decided by the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> was a novelty, and indeed ſeveral perſons before the <hi>Arrians</hi> had ſpoken imprudently enough of the <hi>Divinity of the Son,</hi> and amongſt others he named <hi>Origen, Juſtin Martyr,</hi> and the Council of <hi>Antioch;</hi> as for <hi>Origen,</hi> M. <hi>de Condom</hi> ſaid, he was a ſuſpected author. As to the Council of <hi>Antioch,</hi> 'twas, ſaid he, a Council of <hi>Arrians.</hi> To which M. <hi>Claude</hi> reparty'd, that he was miſtaken, that 'twas a Council held before the <hi>Arrians,</hi> and that it had rejected the term of <hi>conſubſtantial.</hi> As for <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> ha, ſaid M. <hi>de Condom,</hi> that a Martyr e're ſpoke ill of the <hi>Divinity of the Son of God,</hi> I will nee'r beleive it. You may believe My Lord, what you pleaſe, but the thing is however ſo, ſaid M <hi>Claude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M. <hi>de Condom</hi> fell afterwards upon the <hi>Invocation of Saints,</hi> and upon the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for the dead; of the firſt ſaid he, M. <hi>Daille</hi> granted it thirteen hundred years antiquity; and as to the Second, M. <hi>Blondel</hi> owned it very ancient. M. <hi>Claude</hi> replyed, it was not to be thought ſtrange that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> which had ſcraped up and canonized the errors and ſuperſtitions of former ages, ſhould find ſome that were of a ſufficient old date. That he ought to have added how. M. <hi>Daille,</hi> had prov'd that for the ſpace of three hundred years there had not been the leaſt trace ſeen of <hi>the Invocation of Saints,</hi> but eſpecially that it had not the leaſt foundation in Scripture, that he own'd that the prayer was one of the moſt ancient ſuperſtitions, but how that of the ancients was very different from that of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> at this day, and how after all 'twas an error contrary to the principles of the Scripture.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>de Condom</hi> returned again to his compariſon of the Proteſtants with the ancient Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks; concluding their novelty and that of their Church. M. <hi>Claude</hi> made appear this prepoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion was full of injuſtice, and of a dangerous conſequence; unjuſt, becauſe on the one ſide it gave the cauſe to the ſtrongeſt, and to thoſe who have the multitude on their ſide, contrary
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98072:11"/> to what Scripture teaches us, that <hi>We <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ought not to follow the multitude to do ill, Exod</hi> 2.3. for the ſtrongeſt party never fails to accuſe the other of making a new body, a new Church: Unjuſt alſo, becauſe one may take a falſe Antiquity for a real Antiquity, an Antiquity of ſome ages which in effect will be a novelty, for an Antiquity of all ages, which in matter of Religion is the higheſt injuſtice; he added how this prepoſſeſſion was beſides of a dangerous conſequence, for by theſe means from the time errors and ſuperſtitions ſhall inſenſibly be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced into Religion, and that Cuſtom or the School ſhall have authorized them, 'twill be no longer poſſible to oppoſe them or root them out. Thoſe who maintain will be perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually ſaying, that they make a new Church and Religion. Thus the <hi>Phariſees</hi> accuſed I. C. of being an innovator, under pretence that the Diſciples did not obſerve the tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ancients, which themſelves were but innovations; thus the <hi>Jews</hi> accuſed St. <hi>Paul of stirring up ſedition among them through all the World,</hi> and being the head of the <hi>Nazarites,</hi> which they look'd upon as a new Sect. Thus all the Apoſtles were accuſed by the <hi>Pagans</hi> of being <hi>Diſturbers of the publick repoſe, and innovators,</hi> under pretence that they would root out of the hearts of men their ancient errors, and reduce them to the adoration of <hi>one ſole true God Creator of Heaven and of Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M. <hi>de Condom</hi> replied that I. C. was not new, that the Meſſias was expected by the <hi>Jews,</hi> that <hi>John Baptiſt, Anna</hi> the Propheteſs, <hi>Simeon</hi> and the Wiſe Men had own'd him. True he was not new to conſider the thing in it ſelf, ſaid M. <hi>Claude,</hi> for he is yeſterday, and to day, and eternally: But he was new to a whole Nation that expected a Temporal Meſſias, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived not in him any mark of what they expected, he was new in their opinion, in that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the ancient traditions. His Church was new to them, in that it ſeparated it ſelf from the body of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and made a Body apart which they had not yet ſeen. And as to <hi>John Baptist, Anna</hi> the Propheteſs, <hi>Simeon</hi> and the Wiſe men who owned him, what were thoſe but meer partiuclar perſons in compariſon of the whole Body of Sacrificers, Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, Doctors of the Law, and the whole body of the <hi>Jews</hi> in general, who did not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg him, and expected a Terreſtrial Meſſias; wherefore certain it is prepoſſeſſion of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty, which will not allow a body to examine things to the bottom, which does not diſtinguiſh between a falſe and true antiquity, which holds for ancient all that was found out yeſterday, and for new all that is contrary to what was found out yeſterday, is a bad and dangerous prepoſſeſſion, which furniſhes arms both to <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Pagans</hi> againſt the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, and in effect <hi>Calſus</hi> and the other enemies of the <hi>Christians</hi> have not failed to make uſe of them.</p>
            <p>I o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, ſaid M. <hi>de Condom,</hi> that the <hi>Pagans</hi> have repro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ched the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> with their novelty, but the <hi>Christians</hi> have ſhown them that they always beleived the ſame God whom they ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red, and expected the ſame Meſſias. What you ſaid, ſaid M. <hi>Claude,</hi> confirms my ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timent, which is that one ought not to conclude out of prepoſſeſſion infavour of an apparent novelty, but that you muſt pry into the bottom of things, to ſee if what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, is really ſo. That reproach of the <hi>Pagans</hi> proceeded from prejudice and prepoſſeſſion, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> followed my maxime. <hi>For 'twas by the diſcuſſion of the bottom that the Chritians made appear, that tho' they ſeemed new, yet that they were not ſo, and that what they combated in Paganiſms, tho' it ſeemed ancient, was nevertheleſs new.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the Converſation had laſted a long while, near upon five hours, with a great Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation on each ſide, and with a great Attention of the By ſtanders, the Company be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to intermeddle in the Diſcourſe, and the Diſpute ended. After which M. <hi>Claude</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed himſelf to M. <hi>de Condom,</hi> to whom he rendred a great deal of honour, and beſeeched him <hi>that the diverſity of Religions and of ſentiments, might not hinder him from granting him his good will. That f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r his part he would ever preſerve a perfect reſpect and eſteem for the merit of his Perſon.</hi> M. <hi>de Condom</hi> anſwer'd him very civilly, <hi>that he knew him before by his writings, but that he was over joyned to know him alſo by this Coverſation, wherein he had done all that was poſſible for the maintainence of his cauſe, and that there ſhould be no occaſion offered of ſerving him, but he would do it with a willing heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Preſently after M. <hi>de Condom</hi> withdrew, and M. <hi>Claude</hi> having thanked the Company and particularly Madam <hi>La Marechalle de Lorge,</hi> for the attention it had offer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d him, took Leave of <hi>Mademoieſelle de Duras,</hi> to whom he ſaid, that he had defended the truth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and that he had nothing more to do than to pray to God for her, and to exhort her to make a good uſe of what ſhe had heard for the <hi>Confirming her in the Religion wherein God had called her,</hi> without ſuffering her to be ſtaggered by any temptation, and this he ſhould make his requeſt to God for her. <hi>Mademoiſelle de Duras</hi> thanked him very affectionately for the trouble he had taken, and deſired him with ſome emotion of heart to pray to God for her; which M. <hi>Claude</hi> having promiſed her to do, he went his way.</p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 13 line 25. read pertinent, <hi>ibid</hi> line 36 read reject.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:98072:11"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
